Guide to the Stanford Oral History Project Interviews SC1017
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Stanford Oral History Project, Series 1
  - Hansen, Ralph Waldemar, 1979 Aug 21-24; 72_73; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    Manuscripts Librarian (1962-1967), first University Archivist at Stanford (1965-1979) and Chief, Acquisitions Department in the Stanford University Libraries, (1967-1979) Mr. Hansen played a major role in developing library collections, including the creation of the Stanford Library Associates (1974). He also served as acting Assistant Director for Collection Development (1975); Meyer Flood Project coordinator (1978-1979); Palo Alto City Historian (1963-1967); Palo Alto City President (1970-1971).
    Interview covers Hansen's personal background, archival training and path to Stanford; metamorphosis of Stanfordiana Collection into a standard manuscript and archives collection; efforts to gather and centralize university records; difficulties with salaries at Stanford; Hansen's serving in several concurrent management capacities while attending graduate school at Berkeley; marketing of Stanford history to alumni and friends; changes to library staff over the years; development of BALLOTS and library automation; founding of library friends' group (Associates); student unrest in 1960s and 70s, and disruption in libraries; participation in centennial celebration of transcontinental railroad.
    - Transcript (Box 8)
  - Hargadon, Fred, 1984 Jul 2; 74_76; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    Professor of Political Science (1963-1969) and Dean of Admissions (1964-1969) at Swarthmore College, "Dean Fred" came to Stanford in 1969, where he served for 15 years as Dean of Admissions. He resigned in 1984 to accept a position as the Senior Vice President of Administration of the College Board.
    Interview by Roxanne Nilan and Karen Bartholomew; transcribed, 104 pages
  - Hastorf, Barbara, 1986 Apr-May; 77_79; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    Member of the Stanford community since 1969, Mrs. Hastorf speaks about her experiences as a volunteer, with the Stanford overseas program, and as a faculty spouse.
    Interview by Mimi Webb and Joanne O'Donohue.
    - Transcript (Box 8)
  - Hofstadter, Robert, 1985 Jan 17; 283; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Jacobson, David S., 1978 Oct; 80_81; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    Secretary to the University Emeritus, Mr. Jacobson came to work for Stanford in 1936 as assistant to President Donald B. Tresidder after receiving both his A.B. (1930) and L.L.B. (1934) from Stanford. As General Secretary, he played a key role in the development of Stanford's fundraising program.
    Interview by Frederic O. Glover; transcribed, 52 pages
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Jahns, Richard H., 1980 Sep, Oct; 82_84; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    Professor of Geology and Applied Earth Sciences at Stanford from 1964 until his death in 1983; Dean of the School of Earth sciences, 1965-1979; and first holder of Stanford's Welton J. and Maude L. Cook Professorship of Applied Earth sciences, 1977-1983. He combined work at the U.S. Geological survey (1948-1983) with his teaching posts at Cal Tech (1946-1960), Penn State (1960-1964), and Stanford.
    Interview by Harry Press
  - Jessup, Charles R. Bruce, 1980 Feb 29; 85; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 2)
    Clinical Associate Professor, Stanford Medical School; physician, East Palo Alto Medical Clinic. Received his A.B. (1941) and M.D. (1949) from Stanford.
    Interview by Claire Still and Georgiana Kjerulff; 60 minutes
  - Johnson, Olivia, 1982 Mar 9, 1987 Jul 9; 86_89; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Olivia Rolfe entered Stanford in 1914 as one of the 500 women admitted to the University. The next year, she married Stanford geologist Harry Johnson.
    Interview by Harry Press, March 9, 1982. A second interview, by Judy Adams, July 9, 1987
    The interview covers her childhood and family life, the 1906 earthquake, and her studies and life as a student at both Stanford and UCLA.
  - Kaplan, Leah, 1978 May; 90_93; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Director of the Help Center and the first woman staff member to become President of the Faculty Club, Ms. Kaplan served as Assistant Dean of students for Women' s Affairs and as Special Assistant to the Ombudsman. (She was appointed Ombudsman in 1985, after this interview.) A psychiatric counselor to students at Cowell Health Center, Ms. Kaplan acted out of a special interest in the welfare of women students.
    Interview by Margo Davis; donated to the SOHP
  - Keen, Myra, 1977 Jul; 94_96; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Eminent malacologist and curator of Stanford's collection of over 20,000 shells (which was transferred to the California Academy of Sciences), Professor Keen joined the Stanford staff in 1934, was named Curator in 1940 and elected to the faculty of paleontology in 1954.
  - Kendrick, Betty Roth, 97_98, 264; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 3, 7)
    Daughter of Stanford's first Dean of Men under David Starr Jordan, Almon E. Roth, Betty Roth grew up on the Stanford campus and entered Stanford with the class of 1935. The interview focuses on her father's work, and campus life.
    Interview by Fred Glover; transcribed, 53 pages.
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Keohane, Nannerl, 1988 Apr 27; 99; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    President of Wellesley College (1981-1993), Associate Professor of Political Science at Stanford (1973-1981). Professor Keohane was one of the founders of the Feminist Studies program at Stanford.
    Interview by Judy Adams
  - Krauskopf, Konrad, 1986 Dec-1987 Jan; 100_102; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Professor of Geology at Stanford and a leader in his field of geochemistry, Professor Krauskopf received his Ph.D. in Geology from Stanford in 1939 and taught at Stanford from 1935, as an acting instructor, until his retirement in 1976.
  - Levison, Robert Mark, 1899-, 1980 Apr-May; 104_106; 3 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Born in San Francisco in 1899, Levison entered Stanford University in 1917. In 1924 he established the San Francisco insurance brokerage firm of Levison Insurance. Levison has played an active role in Stanford alumni affairs as a member of the Board of Directors of the Alumni Association. In 1935 he joined the original Board of Governors of the Stanford Associates, serving for the maximum six years. He was reelected to the Board in 1973. Levison was awarded the Gold Spike in 1973 for his exceptional work in fundraising activities for Stanford. He is an original member of the Stanford Buck Club and served a full term on the Stanford athletic board. His many civic activities include serving as President of the Jewish Community Center of San Francisco and Vice-President of the National Jewish Welfare Board.
    Interview by Frederic O. Glover; transcribed and bound, 41 pages. Subjects include the development of Stanford University, fundraising, and the Stanford Associates.
    Universities and colleges -- Public relations; Oral histories.; Stanford Fund.; Roth, Almon.; Rothert, Harlow Phelps.; Chandler, Loren Roscoe ("Yank"); Sloss, Leon.; Walker, Frank Fish; Barclay, Thomas S. (Thomas Swain); Irwin, Will; Stanford Associates.; Stanford Alumni Association; Stanford University. Office of Development; Davis, Paul H.; Cuthbertson, Kenneth.; Hutchinson, Eric.; Gunst, Morgan A.; Glover, Frederic O.; Dinkelspiel, Lloyd W.; Edwards, Paul C. (Paul Carroll); Levison family.; Wilbur, Ray L. (Ray Lyman); Keesling, Francis V.; Jacobson, David S.; Pearson, Daryl H.; Mitchell, J. Pearce.; Tresidder, Donald Bertrand; Crothers, George E. (George Edward); McDowell, John Ezra.; Levison, Robert Mark; Roseberry, Louis H.; Reynolds, Harry B.; Price, Harry.; Peck, Templeton.
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Lewis, Janet, 1977 Nov; 107_110; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Poet, novelist and lecturer in creative writing at Stanford, Janet Lewis is best known for her novels The Invasion and The Wife of Martin Guerre. She came to Stanford in 1928 with her husband, poet and Professor of English Yvor Winters and taught creative writing at Stanford.
    Interview by Margo Davis; donated to the SOHP; transcribed and bound, 97 pages
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Lyman, Jing, 1977 Aug 29-Sep2; 284_289; 6 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Manson, Clara, 1980 Oct; 111; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Librarian at Lane Library, Stanford Medical School, in San Francisco (1948-1949) and after its move to the Stanford campus (1959-1971).
    Interview by Claire Still; 60 minutes
  - Mendelowitz, Daniel M., 1978 Dec; 112; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Emeritus Professor of Art, who taught at Stanford for 36 years--a talented artist and gentle commentator on the history of art; received his A.B. (1926) and M.A. (1927) from Stanford. Professor Mendelowitz died in 1980.
    Interview by Frederic O. Glover
  - Mitchell, Sidney, 1990 Mar 21; 281; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Murphy, Michael H., 1980 Jun; 113_114; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Author, and founder of the Esalen Institute, Mr. Murphy received his A.B. in psychology (1952) from Stanford, where he was active in student affairs.
    Interview by John Callaghan; 120 minutes
  - Page, Virginia, 1987 May 28; 279_280; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Purdy, Ann Peril, 1977 Jun 16; 278; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Ricker, Christine, 1979 Dec; 117; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    As Director of Dining Halls and the Stanford Union for 37 years, Ms. Ricker was responsible for student food services. She retired in 1958.
    Interview by Harry Press; 60 minutes.
  - Rosenzweig, Robert M., 1983 Jan-Mar; 118_122; 5 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Vice-President for Public Affairs at Stanford (1974-1983), and now President of the A.A.U., Dr. Rosenzweig came to Stanford in 1962 after receiving his Ph.D. from Yale and working briefly at Amherst and with the U.S. Department of Education. He first served as Assistant Dean of the Graduate Division (1962-1967) and as Associate Provost (1967-1971). He became Vice-Provost and Presidential Advisor under President Richard Lyman in 1971 and in 1974 became Stanford's first Vice-President of Public Affairs. This interview provides especially good insight into years of great administrative changes, student activism and a change in the University's attitude towards governmental relations.
    Interview by Karen Bartholomew and Donald Carlson; transcribed, 103 pages
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Roth, Betty and Roth, Miriam, 124; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    Daughters of Almon E. Roth, Comptroller of the University from 1919 to 1937 and Stanford graduate, class of 1909. The interview covers the projects completed during Mr. Roth's tenure as comptroller, including Stanford Stadium, Sunken Diamond, and the Stanford Golf Course.
    Betty and Miriam Roth, daughters of Almon Roth: growing up on campus, students they knew when they were children, reminiscences of their parents and their own days as Stanford students.
    Interview by Robert de Roos
  - Schofield, Mary, 1987 Apr 21; 125; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
    A Stanford graduate, class of 1929, Miss Schofield worked in the Hoover Institution Library from 1933 until her retirement. She donated her large collection of children's books to the Department of Special Collections, Stanford University Library.
    Interview by Judy Adams.
    Schofield has a long association with Stanford, as child of students, student herself, and employee. Interview describes her history and background on her parents.
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Sears, Robert Richardson, 1982; 126_136; 11 audiocassette(s) (Box 3-4)
    David Starr Jordan Professor of Psychology, emeritus, Bob Sears returned to Stanford in 1953 after teaching at Harvard, Yale, and Iowa State University. The son of Professor Jesse B. Sears, he was born in Palo Alto in 1908 and received his A. B. from Stanford in 1929, his Ph.D. from Yale in 1932. He has also served as Dean of Humanities and Sciences (1961-1969) and as chairman of the Psychology Department during years of great growth. He is particularly well known for his work in the social psychological development of children, in personality and motivation.
    Interview by Frederic O. Glover; transcribed and bound, 107 pages
    A separate set of interviews, conducted by Hamilton Cravens of Iowa State University's Program in the History of Science and Technology, and donated to the SOHP, focuses on Professor Sears' contributions to the field of child development. The first set is transcribed, 117 pages The second set is transcribed, 80 pages
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Snyder, Rixford K., 1979 Mar-Apr; 137_138; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    Long-time Dean of Admissions (1950-1969), Professor Snyder also served as Associate Professor of History (1940-1943, 1946-1969) after receiving his A.B. (1930), A.M. (1934), and Ph.D. (1940) in history from Stanford. Director of the Alumni Travel Study Program of the Stanford Alumni Association from 1969 until his formal retirement in 1974, but kept a workspace in the Travel/Study office, where he compiled his memoirs and continued to go on alumni trips well into his 70s.
    Interview by Frederic O. Glover and George Knoles; transcribed and bound, 80 pages
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Sterling, Wallace
    Stanford University President, 1949-1968.
    - "Remembering Wallace Sterling", 1985 Aug 9; 139_140; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
      Peter C. Allen came back to Stanford in 1946 as Editor of the Stanford Review, the Stanford Alumni Association magazine. He first met Dr. Sterling when he and Fred Glover interviewed him after the Big Game in 1948. Allen succeeded Glover as Director of Information in 1953 and later became the first Director of the News and Publications Service. He was University Editor when he retired in 1977 and he was University Editor Emeritus at the time of this taping session.
      Ernest C. Arbuckle knew Dr. Sterling from the time they were both graduate students in 1933. They were good friends when Dr. Sterling was at Caltech and at the Huntington Library, and were close personal friends by the time Arbuckle was elected a University trustee (1954-58). Dr. Sterling appointed him Dean of the Graduate School of Business in 1958 and he served until 1968. Arbuckle was also Chairman of the board of Stanford Research Institute (now SRI International) 1966-70. But he left the deanship in 1968 to become Chairman of the Board of Wells Fargo Bank and Wells Fargo Co. He served a second term on the Board of Trustees, 1973-76. He was elected Chairman of the Board of Saga Corporation in 1978 and served until 1982. [Mr. Arbuckle and his wife Katherine were killed in an automobile accident on January 17, 1986.]
      Alf Brandin also knew Dr. Sterling from the early 30s when he was a member of Stanford's "Vow Boys" football team. He was appointed University Business Manager in 1946 by President Donald Tresidder and continued to serve in that capacity under Dr. Sterling. In 1953 Brandin became Executive Officer of the Stanford Land Development Program as well, and the following year was made Vice President for Business Affairs. He left Stanford in 1970 to become Senior Vice President and member of the Executive Committee of the Board of Utah Construction and Mining Company [known as Utah International Inc. when this session was held].
      E. Howard Brooks was an Acting Instructor of History in 1949 when he first met Dr. Sterling. He called on the president to ask if he would assist in judging a graduate student essay contest. (He did.) In 1951 Brooks became Assistant Director of Admissions under Professor Rixford Snyder. In 1957 Provost Frederick Terman tapped Brooks for the position of Assistant to the Provost and Director of the Summer Session. From 1965 to 1971 Brooks held the position of Vice Provost. When this taping session took place, he was Provost Emeritus of the Claremont Colleges of California.
      Donald T. Carlson returned to Stanford in 1951 as Assistant Director of Information to Director Fred Glover. His first meeting with Dr. Sterling had been a year earlier when he was Executive Secretary of Oregon State College. He served in the General Secretary's Office (now Development) 1952-54, as Assistant to the President, 1954-61, and in both the University Relations Office and President's Office, 1961-68. He was Director of University Relations in the Office of Public Affairs at the time of this taping.
      Kenneth M. Cuthbertson came back to the University in 1954 as Assistant to the President, replacing Robert Wert as Dr. Sterling's budget control officer. He very soon became Dr. Sterling's point man in all matters of financial consequence to the University. Cuthbertson was named Vice President for Finance in 1959, and later took on the responsibility for managing the University's fund raising program as well. He was the principal University officer responsible for the successful conduct of two major fund raising campaigns, the $100,000,000 Plan of Action for a Challenging Era, 1962-64, and the Campaign for Stanford, 1972-77, that reached a total of $304,000,000. From 1970 to 1977 he was Vice President for Development. He held that title as emeritus and was President of the James Irvine Foundation when this taping took place.
      Frederic O. Glover joined President Donald Tresidder's staff as Director of Information in 1946. His acquaintance with Wallace Sterling began in the early 30s when he was training for the Stanford boxing team and Dr. Sterling was a graduate student working out regularly in the gymnasium. Glover moved into the President's Office to replace Tom Spragens as Assistant to the President in 1954, and became Executive Assistant to the President in 1959. He served in that capacity until Dr. Sterling's retirement in 1968 and continued with President Kenneth Pitzer. In 1970 Glover became Secretary to the University, continuing his responsibility for trustee affairs, a title he held as emeritus at the time of this taping.
      Robert H. Moulton, Jr. came back to Stanford from the Ford Foundation in 1957 as Assistant to the President. He was Dr. Sterling's aide for financial forecasting during the planning period that led to the PACE campaign of the early 60s. In 1960 he was also made Associate Director of "Project M" (for Monster), when a two-mile-long electron accelerator was only a pile of plans on paper—lots of paper. Moulton continued to be an assistant to Dr. Sterling until 1968. He retired from the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center in 1983 as Associate Director Emeritus.
      Lyle M. Nelson left the vice presidency for University Relations at the University of Michigan in 1961 to become Stanford's Director of University Relations in Dr. Sterling's administration. He was public relations and political counsel to Dr. Sterling for the remainder of his tenure and continued to be his informal counsel through his years as chancellor. Nelson served in the faculty as Professor of Communication and Journalism and as Chairman of the Department of Communication. He was nearing emeritus status when this taping session took place.
      Nine men who worked closely with President J. E. Wallace Sterling during his administration gathered together in the Stanford Faculty Club one afternoon following his death (July 1, 1985) to share their thoughts about the kind of man he was, the problems he faced and how he dealt with them, and not least, some of his accomplishments.
      The Participants: Peter C. Allen, '36 Ernest C. Arbuckle, '33, MBA '36 Alf E. Brandin, '36 E. Howard Brooks, '42, M.A.'47, Ph.D.'50 Donald T. Carlson, '47 Kenneth M. Cuthbertson, '40, MBA '47 Frederic 0. Glover, '33 Robert H. Moulton, Jr. '40 Lyle M. Nelson, Oregon '41
      - Transcript (Box 9)
    - "Reminscences, 1949-1960," interviews with Glover, Allen, Carlson, 1977 Mar-Apr; 252_259; 8 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    - Anecdotes, 260_261; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 7)
  - Stolz, Lois Meek, 1977 Jul; 141_142, 262_263; 4 audiocassette(s) (Box 4, 7)
    Professor of Psychology at Stanford since 1946, Professor Stolz is well-known for her work in child psychology and child care, and has long maintained an interest in Stanford women. She was active in her field until her death in 1984.
    Interview by Margo Davis; donated to the SOHP; transcribed and bound, 80 pages
    Psychological research.; Psychology.; Oral histories.; Photoprints.; Interviews.; Stanford University. Department of Psychology. Faculty; Davis, Margo.; Stanford Oral History Project.; Stolz, Lois Meek
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Swank, Raynard C., 1980 Sep 25; 143; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    Director of Libraries at Stanford from 1948-1962, Dr. Swank undertook a badly-needed revitalization of the library system, providing more effective service to instruction and research.
    Interview by Frederic O. Glover. Description of campus (by Glover) in 1948 to emphasize changes during Swank's 14 years; Swank/Wilson report on library needs 1946-47; focus on service to undergraduates, including initial planning for undergraduate library; Stanford fundraising campaigns, and omission of libraries from them; collection building under Swank; centralizing records and inclusion of branch libraries in union catalog; Technical Information Service that served industrial park businesses; increasing humanities resources to match sciences; changes in library science education since 1960s.
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982., 1971-1978
    Engineer and educator Frederick Emmons Terman began his teaching career at Stanford in 1925 and became a full professor in 1937. In 1937, he also became head of the Electrical Engineering Department. As Dean of the School of Engineering (1945-1960) and as Provost (1955-1965) and Vice President (1959-1965) of the University, Terman played a key role in developing University faculty, research facilities and funding. Interviews done by Bancroft Library, UC Berkeley.
    Subjects covered by the interviews include his teaching and research career at Stanford University, the National Defense Research Committee, the Harvard Radio Research Laboratory, post-war research at Stanford, and the electronics industry, especially the Hewlett-Packard Company and its founders William R. Hewlett and David Packard.
    General
    These interviews were a joint project of the History of Science and Technology Program at the University of California at Berkeley and the Stanford Oral History Project at Stanford University.
    Electronics; Science -- History.; Microelectronics industry -- United States -- History.; High technology industries -- California; Oral histories.; Klystrons.; Engineering -- United States -- History.; Microelectronics industry -- California -- Santa Clara County.; High technology -- Research.; Harvard University. Radio Research Laboratory.; Ginzton, Edward L. (Edward Leonard); Hewlett, William R.; United States. Office of Scientific Research and Development. National Defense Research Committee.; Ryan, Harris J. (Harris Joseph); Stanford University. Department of Electrical Engineering; Hewlett Packard Company; Bancroft Library. History of Science and Technology Program.; Bush, Vannevar; Packard, David, 1912-1996; Webster, David Locke; Hansen, W. W. (William Webster); Terman, Frederick Emmons, 1900-1982; Varian, Russell Harrison
    - Transcript (Box 9)
  - Vickers, Joseph, 1984 Nov; 144; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)
    A Stanford alumnus of the class of 1912, Judge Vickers had a distinguished legal career, part of it serving as a Judge of the Superior Court of Los Angeles. Vickers had an extensive history of volunteer work on Stanford's behalf.
    Interview by Donald Carlson and Edward Raleigh
  - Whitaker, Virgil, 1982 May; 145_146; 2 audiocassette(s) (Box 4)